My receiver is fully restored. And yours
will never be right until you replace
every electrolytic capacitor in it. My
receiver's all original. Works great. If
it ain't broke, don't fix it. That's a
ticking time bomb. Remind me how much
your repair bill was?
Full recap, break fix repair, one of the
longest running debates in the vintage
audio community. And both sides have
compelling arguments. But after
servicing well over a thousand pieces of
vintage audio gear, I can tell you that
blanket statements are where this debate
really goes off the rails. So in this
video, I'm going to go over the pros and
the cons of each side of the argument,
and hopefully bring some clarity to this
debate so that you can make a better
decision when it comes to your piece of
vintage audio gear.
I think the best way to break the ice
with this discussion is with a real
world example. A few years ago, I had a
customer bring me two Pioneer receivers,
an SX-1080 that he wanted me to do a
full overhaul on, and an SX-850 that he
just wanted me to get back up and
running so that he could sell it to help
fund the restoration of the 1080. I
performed what I call a break fix repair
on the SX-850. That means that I only
replaced the components that were
necessary to get it back up and running.
In this case, the unit was stuck in
protection. I replaced some blue Sanyo
caps in the protect circuit, got it back
up and running, did some additional
routine maintenance, fully tested it,
and sent it back to the customer. But
here's where things get interesting.
Instead of selling the unit, he decided
to keep it and put it into regular use
in his home. And sure enough, two to
three years later, it came back to the
bench with another issue. This time,
power supply failure due to bad
electrolytic capacitors. So you might be
thinking, "Ben, you should have just
recapped the thing and you wouldn't have
been in this situation." But I still
think I made the right decision in that
specific scenario, and by the end of
this video, you're going to understand
why.
Not all electrolytic capacitors age or
fail in the same way. Now, it's true
that all electrolytics have a limited
lifespan, but I found time and again
during full restorations that over 90%
of the parts that I pull are technically
still good. If you've watched any of my
Novalux Legacy reviews on monster
receivers, you've probably noticed a
pattern. I show a giant baggy full of
all the parts I pulled out of the unit,
and then a little tiny cup with maybe
three or four failed electrolytic
capacitors in it. And believe it or not,
a lot of times those units will continue
to fundamentally work even with those
bad parts in place. So, how do we know
which capacitors to replace and which
ones to leave alone? For that, we need
experience.
If you're just getting started in audio
repair, one of the most powerful tips I
can give is test every electrolytic
capacitor that you pull out of a unit.
You're going to start recognizing
patterns that will better inform future
work. So, let me give you some examples
of some of the things that I've observed
over the years. The smaller a capacitor
is, and the closer it is to a heat
source, the higher the probability of
failure. The Pioneer SX-1250 is a great
example of this.
I work on so many SX-1250s that I built
a dedicated test jig out of a parts unit
for verifying these vertical cards. The
power supply in the 1250 is located in
this location, and this is where most of
the heat in the unit is generated.
Here's an SX-1250 power supply board in
original condition. And if we look at
the capacitors here, you can see the
shrinkage of the wrappers. That
indicates exposure to high heat. The
ironic thing is these capacitors, since
they're large, are probably going to
test just fine. These are rated at 220
microfarad 80 V. Let's take a look.
Looks fine. Let's try the other one.
Yeah, those caps are still technically
good. I wouldn't leave them in there
because of all the
heat exposure and obvious shrinkage, but
they technically still work. Now, this
little capacitor in here that's nested
between two hot regulator transistors,
I don't think that one's going to have
done nearly as well. Let's check it out.
No good.
Here's a driver board from an SX-1250.
You can see there's not a lot of
capacitors on this board. That's because
this is a direct coupled output section.
These big capacitors here are likely
fine due to their size. These ones
usually develop a little bit of ESR, but
they don't cause the circuit to stop
working. The real offender on this board
is actually this little tiny blue
tantalum capacitor here. This one
develops resistance over time, and if it
gets bad enough, it'll cause the
protection circuit to false trigger.
But, I only know that because I've
worked on over 20 of these units, and
I've had to track that failure in the
past. So, what I'm trying to say is that
doing effective break-fix repair
requires experience. So, it's kind of a
limiting factor. While we're on the
topic of the SX-1250, rebuilding the
power supply and the power amplifier
section in general is usually required
if you want your unit to be stable for
the long term. But, the preamp on the
other hand, the capacitors that were
used in there, although sometimes they
develop high ESR, especially those
orange low leakage caps, they don't keep
the circuit from functioning. And
there's not a lot of heat there. So,
usually you can get away with just
cleaning the controls, and the preamp's
going to continue to run just fine. But,
you're not going to know these things if
you don't have the experience. So,
that's where recapping comes in a lot of
the times. People are unsure. They just
want that peace of mind that
everything's been done, and it's just
one less variable that they have to
worry about. A lot of capacitors also
just have inferior construction or a
fatal design flaw. The multi-section
cans that are found a lot of 1960s
equipment are made with a jelly roll of
paper, and those have a very high
failure rate. In fact, when it comes to
1960s electrolytics, I don't really
trust any of them at this point. By the
time we get to the late '60s, early
'70s, the capacitor technology developed
quite a bit and the parts become a
little bit more reliable. Once we get
into the late '70s, '80s, we start to
see a lot of capacitors that just have
poor construction and just fail over
time. That's going to be the blue Sanyo
caps seen in the later Pioneer devices.
Those turn into resistors. Uh the purple
caps in Yamaha, in McIntosh, Levinson,
Krell, you'll find these brown ROE caps
or Roderstein caps. They have a Bakelite
case and once that Bakelite cracks, the
electrolyte leaks out and becomes crusty
on the outside. Those caps always test
bad. I don't I don't even test them
anymore. I just pull them out and
replace them. Now, you might be thinking
at this point, if there's so many
failure modes and so many
replace-on-site capacitors, why don't I
just replace all of the electrolytics
and be done with it? Well, there's a few
other variables that we need to
consider.
If you test capacitors as you pull them
out for replacement, you're probably
going to notice that a lot of them will
test closer to value and lower in ESR
than the parts that you're about to put
in their place. And going along with
that, we don't know the exact lifespan
of a lot of these new capacitors that
we're putting into units. If they
haven't been sourced from a reputable
vendor and manufacturer, you could be
putting an inferior part in your unit
and doing that 20 or 30 times over. Bulk
recapping can also increase the
probability of unintentional damage.
Imagine we have a unit that's got one
bad capacitor in a single board. If we
flip that board down, replace the bad
part, and put it back, it's a minimally
invasive. But, if you want to do a whole
recap on that board and it's still
connected inside of the unit while
you're working, you could be flipping
that back 20, 30 times as you're
replacing all of the capacitors. And now
every one of those electronic
connections has been weakened. And if
one of those breaks while you're working
on it and you don't notice it, you can
put the entire thing back together and
when you fire it up, one of the features
is non-functional and then you have to
go track it down. Another thing that can
happen is if you're not experienced with
soldering and desoldering yet, you can
end up causing irreparable damage to the
traces and pads. So, if some capacitors
are completely fine to stay, but others
should absolutely be replaced, maybe
doing a full recap is the best way to
cover our bases.
But, that adds additional cost and
increases the probability of board
damage and mistakes. So, how do we
choose? I'm going to review a table
showing the pros and cons of each repair
philosophy, and along the way I'll mark
the positive aspects in green. This
table is arranged with break fix repair
on the left and full recap on the right.
So, let's start with the first entry.
Break fix repair is relatively
inexpensive. Well, full recaps are
almost always expensive. You're dealing
with more parts cost, and if you're
paying somebody else to do it, it's a
lot more labor cost as well. So, in this
case, we're going to mark this one
for
break fix repair.
Next up, break fix repair is minimally
invasive, while full recaps cause more
stress on the traces, pads, and wiring.
So, we'll chalk that up again on the
break fix repair side.
Break fix repair is easy to backtrack.
But, what do I mean by that?
If we are troubleshooting an issue and
we replace one suspect capacitor, if we
put that part in backwards or forget to
solder an adjacent solder joint or
something, if we power it on and
something's not working, we know exactly
where we were and we can go back and
inspect the work. If you end up doing a
full recap on a unit, especially if
you're not testing in between boards, if
you power the thing up and it's not
working properly anymore, it's a much
harder task to go back and figure out
what you did wrong. So, break fix repair
gets the
positive green in this case again.
Doing break fix repair can help you
learn patterns over time and build
experience. When you're doing a full
recap, you might fix an issue, but you
won't know exactly which cap caused the
issue and what circuit it was in. So,
when you're doing a full recap, there's
just a lot of information that you miss
out on. So, again, that gives us green
to break fix repair.
Break fix repair takes experience to do
successfully. You need quite a bit of
background knowledge to know where to
even look and which capacitors tend to
fail in the first place. When you're
doing a full recap, you don't need as
much of that background knowledge, and
you may actually be able to fix a
stubborn issue that would be very hard
to trace if you're doing break fix
repair. So, in this case, I'm going to
give the green to the full recap side.
A break fix repair might leave behind
parts that are going to fail in the near
future. When we do a full recap, you're
starting from a clean slate, assuming
you used good quality parts.
Break fix repair preserves originality.
And this can be important if you're
dealing with a highly collectible piece,
or you're dealing with a component that
people say has a magic sound. If you
change the original parts, it's going to
ruin the sonic character of the unit.
That's where preserving originality
might come into play. On the other side,
when you do a full recap with fresh
parts, you're probably going to be
closer to the original specification as
the device was designed because you're
not dealing with old drifted parts that
are starting to fail. So, in this one,
I'm going to give the green to both
sides. They both have strong advantages.
Break fix repair stabilizes resale
value. And what I mean by that is if
you've got a device that's not working
properly, if you go to try to sell that,
you're going to get way less for it than
if it fundamentally works and it's been
tested. So, a lot of times by completing
a simple break fix repair, you can
drastically increase the value of a unit
that's in non-working condition.
Full recaps, this can kind of go both
ways. This is why I put may increase
resale value if done properly. Sometimes
doing a full recap hurts the value of a
unit. There's other times where the
difference between a serviced piece and
a restored piece or fully recapped piece
is in the thousands of dollars. So, in
this case, I'm going to give the green
to both again. They both have clear
advantages.
Okay, that completes the table. Let's
see if we can draw any conclusions.
First, let's look at the negatives of
each. When we're dealing with break fix
repair, it has a barrier to entry. You
really need quite a bit of experience to
be successful with this method. It also
can leave parts behind that may soon
fail, and that's the exact example we
saw with the SX-850 repair that I showed
at the beginning of the video.
The negative sides of doing a full recap
are that it's going to be more expensive
parts and labor wise.
You can cause more stress to the traces,
pads, and wiring, especially if you
don't have a lot of soldering
experience.
It's going to increase the risk of
mistakes because there's just more parts
being replaced. And you don't learn as
much because you're not replacing one
part at a time and doing AB testing, you
just gain a lot less information while
you're doing the work.
So, with all those negatives in mind,
when might a full recap be appropriate?
If you are troubleshooting a circuit
with the conventional break fix repair
method and you're really stuck, you're
at your wit's end, doing what we call a
capacitor shotgun replacement might be
in order as a last resort to fix a
stubborn issue.
If you just want some peace of mind
knowing that all of the parts are new,
starting from a clean slate can be
valuable.
If you are noticing issues where maybe
one channel is sounding kind of dull,
the frequency response doesn't match,
replacing all of the capacitors might
help improve the performance of the
unit.
If you're looking to drastically
increase the resale value of a specific
unit, maybe you're doing the repair
yourself, that could be a good reason to
do a full recap.
On the break-fix side of things, we got
a lot of green here. It's relatively
inexpensive compared to a full recap,
minimally invasive, meaning you're going
to have less opportunities to make a
mistake or cause damage to the unit. If
you do make a mistake, it's easy to jump
back right to where you were working.
Allows you to learn patterns over time
and gain experience, preserve the
originality of collectible units, and
also stabilizes resale value. In a lot
of cases, you'll be better off
financially doing a break-fix repair
over a full recap. It really just
depends on the specific unit.
It may seem like I'm more of an advocate
for the break-fix repair philosophy. So,
if that's the case, why do you see so
many full restorations on my channel?
First of all, it's what the customer is
usually asking for. I have a very long
backlog, so if a customer has been
waiting in line for 6 months up to a
year to get in,
they're not going to want me to just
replace a couple of parts. They want the
whole thing gone through. So, that's
usually why I end up doing the full
restorations.
Now, just because I'm doing a full
restoration and replacing all the caps
in the unit, it doesn't mean that I'm
skipping the break-fix repair steps.
Every piece of equipment that comes into
my shop goes on the bench and gets a
baseline test before I do any work at
all. And then if I find issues with the
unit, I repair those circuits one by one
until the entire unit is working, and
then I go through and do the full
restoration. Especially if it's a unit
that I've never worked on before. On
something like a Pioneer SX-1250, if the
customer knows they want a full overhaul
on it, I just start with my process, gut
it, and rebuild the thing. But in most
of the cases, I'm going to be testing
and completing circuit repairs first,
and then doing the full restoration
afterwards. And that's exactly what I do
on Patreon. So, if you're learning audio
repair and you'd like to follow along
with that process of bench testing,
repair, and restoration, head down to
the description for a link to the
Patreon page.
So, at the end of the day, who's right?
The full recap crowd or the if it ain't
broke, don't fix it crowd? Well, the
answer is both, but it really depends on
the scenario. So, let me take you
through a handful of hypothetical
examples and hopefully this will clear
everything up. You own a repair shop and
you've got a customer that's on a budget
and needs their unit back fast. Break
fix repair, good idea.
You're a beginner with limited soldering
and desoldering skills and you're taking
on your first valuable monster receiver.
Full recap, bad idea.
You're an experienced hobbyist and you
just landed your holy grail receiver and
you want to go all out. Full recap, good
idea.
The left channel of your integrated amp
starts dropping out. Whenever you smack
the top of the unit, it comes right
back. Full recap, bad idea. That's
probably a relay issue.
You own a repair shop, you've got a
customer with a decent budget and they
want their unit to run reliably for
years. Full recap, good idea. You just
landed a $300 receiver for $20 on
Facebook Marketplace. You want to get it
back up and running so that you can flip
it and make a profit. Full recap, bad
idea.
You're a museum curator preparing
exhibit of 1960s Marantz equipment.
You'd like the devices to fundamentally
work for demonstration, but you also
want the insides to look original for
when you put them on display. Break fix
repair, good idea. Listening to a
stranger in a Facebook group claiming
there's a universal right and wrong way
to do things, bad idea.
I hope this brings some clarity to the
debate and the next time this comes up,
you can better justify your position
based on your current skill level, your
budget, and the specific piece that
you're working on. And if someone tells
you you're wrong, send them a link to
this video. I look forward to seeing
them in the comments. Thanks for
stopping by. We'll catch you on the next
one.